MANUEL PAUL ANIL KUMAR JOSEPH

33/11, Victoria Road, 1st Cross, Xavier Layout

jmpak80@gmail.com

+919731032150

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Bangalore - 560047

I am a software developer with over 7 years of experience. I have worked with multiple technologies performing different roles ranging from developer to build cop. For most of my career I have been building complex business software. I recently completed my masters degree in Machine learning and since then I have spent a huge portion of my time building applications which harness information from the web.

SKILL SET

- Programming Languages: Ruby, Java, Haskell, Python, C#, JavaScript, SQL etc.
- Other technologies: EC2, S3, Django, Ruby on Rails, Winforms, Hudson, cruisecontrol etc.
- Current Interests: Sentiment analysis, Apps around data from twitter.
- Methodologies: XP, TDD
- **Technical Papers:** Timothy Baldwin, Manuel Paul Anil Kumar Joseph: Restoring Punctuation and Casing in English Text. Australasian Conference on Artificial Intelligence 2009

EXPERIENCE

Peek India (http://www.getpeek.in) - June 2009 - Present: Lead Developer

Peek is a simple device that sends and receives email on the go. I have worked in the role of the lead developer on the server team. Successfully developed software and services that enabled launching of the device in India. I worked on EC2-S3 backend enhancements and modifications for India, Exchange enhancements and modifications and was responsible for the deployment and maintenance of Peek servers on EC2

Eos Systems (http://www.eossystems.com) - Dec 2008 - June 2009: Consultant

Consulted at Eossytems working on www.ranker.com. Worked as a lead developer. Mentored other junior developers on the team. Was responsible to setting up their automated build and deployment process.

July 2008 - Dec 2008: Entrepreneur

Explored various approaches in machine learning and natural language processing - sentiment analysis a opinion gathering from web corpus and keyword generation. I built a tool that analyzed sentiments in user reviews and demoed it to a company in UK. These efforts were huge learning experiences, but they did not work out financially

Also conducting a course in "Harnessing Collective Intelligence" for 30 gifted (GPA 8.5 and above) students at PES Institute of Technology, Bangalore, India.

Worked for Thoughtworks India Pvt Ltd as an application developer from September 2002 to September 2007.

Client: Leading bank in Australia (March 2007 - July 2007)

The client is a leading bank in Australia. This project involved making a new product(superannuation product) available online. As a developer I worked during the initial inception of the project. I went over to the client site to gain conext before coming back and starting off the project in Bangalore. The application is a web app using **JSR 168** specification for portals. It also involved using TIBCO for integrating the customer information system and a third part superannuation product.

Client: Leading train retailer for UK (December 2006 - Feb 2007)

The client is a leading train retailer in the UK. They provide impartial service, giving users instant access to the full range of over journey and fare combinations within the whole of the UK. The client requirement is to replace their legacy application with a new application employing new and scalable technology. Manuel worked as a developer for this project. As a developer, I was responsible for the extension of the credit card authentication functionality to ensure fraud detection. I was also responsible for helping out Business Analysts and Quality Assurance Analysts with testing the application.

Client: US Based Equipment Leasing firm (April 2006- December 2006)

I worked as a developer for this project to build a fleet management application for the rail car leasing division of the client. While gradually replacing a legacy system, the project went beyond mere application development to bring about process improvement in the customer's business. I have been an integral part of this team which works distributed from Chicago and Bangalore. As a part of this project, I traveled to Chicago for a month to work with the team there.

Client: Large UK based retail chain (November 2005 - April 2006)

I worked as a developer in the internationalization of a Point of Sale application used in the UK thus far, to be extended for use in Spain and France. The application is based on **Java 1.3/1.4**, **Swing**, **XML**, **Web sphere and Oracle**.

Client: Worlds Leading Equipment Leasing company (August 2005 - November 2005)

Manuel was a developer on front end leasing system for maintenance and leasing of heavy equipment and machinery. The project involved a configuration application which enables the business the create instances of business units with separate data sets specific to that part of the world. This eventually enables clients business to be streamlined and defined across the world. The main technologies include J2EE, Hibernate and Core Java.

Internal Project: Resource Management Application (April 2005 – August 2005)

I was involved in two releases of the project, which deals with RM, Revenue Forecasting, Demand Forecasting etc. The two releases I worked on consisted of: Enhancing the system, to use webservices. This enabled the system to be used from outside the Thoughtworks network.

Client: A Medical Malpractice Insurance Company, USA (Feb 2004 – April 2005)

I have worked on this project as a .NET developer for about 12 months since the very initial stages of the project. I was involved in multiple releases of the project, which involved completely replacing their existing claims management system. The three releases Manuel has worked on consisted of: Event management release to generate/manage daily events, triggers and alarms; Rating and Rate Management release was the rating engine

for the insurance provider, Quoting Release, which involves quoting an insurance policy. The project was built on the .NET platform with C# as the programming language. It also involved working with COM wrappers in .NET for Microsoft Office components for integration with the new system.

Client: A Leading leasing company, USA (Sept 2002 -Feb 2004)

I worked in the creation of a large back-end leasing application. The application architecture consists of a Swing front end using XML/HTTP to talk to a Servlet/EJB server, which used JDBC to talk to the database. It uses EJBs to maintain sessions. Specific products used include **WebLogic 5.1**, **6.1**, **Oracle 8i**, **and JDK 1.3**, **1.3.1**.

EDUCATION

Masters of Software Systems Engineering at the University of Melbourne completed in 2008.

Bachelor of Engineering (CSc): Visveswariah Technological University, Karnataka, INDIA, completed in 2002.

References

References available on request.